Finding Aid for Calvin Thomas Papers, 1838-1940
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Calvin Thomas Papers 1838-1940, 1872-1919
Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.
1 oversize folders
3 linear feet
86180 Aa 2; Ac
Professor of German at the University of Michigan and Columbia; mostly correspondence of Thomas with his family, professional colleagues, publisher, etc.; also some correspondence of his wife after his death; speeches, lecture notes, biographical sketches; papers include material on language studies at Michigan and Columbia, attitudes of academia toward Germans in World War I, accounts of European travels in 1877, 1896, and 1900; Civil War letter of Steven Thomas, Calvin's father.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Harold A. Thomas and Dr. Harold A. Thomas, Jr. (donor no. 3764 ) and came to the library in 1961.
The collection is open to research.
Calvin Thomas was born at Lapeer, Michigan on October 28, 1854. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1874 with a specialization in Greek and Latin. He taught high school in Grand Rapids for three years, then in 1877, he went to Leipzig for a brief period of study. In 1878, he came back to Ann Arbor as an instructor in German. He achieved some prominence as a scholar of Germanic languages and literature, particularly of Goethe and Schiller. In 1896, he was called to Columbia University where he taught until his death, November 4, 1919.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/personal material; Correspondence; Lectures and addresses; Journals/diary; Scrapbooks; Other family members papers; and Publications.
Subjects:
Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Cheever, Byron William, 1841-1888.; Columbia University.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Europe--Description and travel.; First Unitarian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lapeer (Mich.); Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.; Voyages and travels.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 10th (1863-1865); Universität Leipzig.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.; Thomas family.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Erskine, John, 1879-1951.; Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958.; Gildersleeve, Virginia C.; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; Thomas, Steven Van Renssler, 1831-1905.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/personal material
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (include preliminary autobiography and notes written by his wife)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (include portraits of Thomas and other family members)
  - Diplomas, citations, etc. (Folder Ac)
- Correspondence
  (mainly letters among family members and Thomas with his publisher)
  - 1838 (Box 1)
    (letter to Mrs. Sarah Allen from her daughter Louisa)
  - 1861-1865 (Box 1)
    (include letter of Steven Thomas while serving in the 10th Michigan Cavalry)
    (in oversize folder Ac)
  - 1872-1879 (Box 1)
    (microfilm copy available for 1874-1877)
  - 1880-1887 (Box 1)
  - 1884-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1888-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894-1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1917 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1917 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1918 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Mrs. Eleanor Thomas
    - 1919 letters of condolence, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - 1932-1940 (Box 1)
- Lectures and addresses
  - Goethe's Faust, in two parts undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Notebook on Goethe's Faust (Box 1)
  - Lectures on Ibsen, in six parts 1886, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Schiller 1894 (Box 2)
  - Rousseau; an address (Box 2)
  - Other writings and miscellaneous undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Poems and translations of poetry 1874-1916 (Box 2)
  - Notebook containing translations of poetry, largely Sanskrit (Box 2)
  - Notebook of quotes entitled "Gems from the King's Treasury" (Box 2)
  - Notebook of quotations written "In Memoriam Jennie S. Thomas -- Died December 1880" 1881 (Box 2)
- Journals/diary
  - Diary, 1872 (Box 2)
  - Journal January 10, 1873-September 16, 1876 (Box 2)
    (microfilm copy available for July 10, 1874-July 8, 1877)
  - Journal September 24, 1876-March 10, 1878 (Box 2)
  - Journal April 2, 1878-December 13, 1880 (Box 2)
  - Typed excerpts from journals 1873-1877 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook 1874-1885 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1884-1889 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1889-1906 (Box 3)
- Other family members papers
  - Paul Thomas Papers 1919 (Box 3)
  - Harold Thomas diary, 1895-1896 (Box 3)
  - Harold Thomas journal 1900 (Box 3)
  - Eleanor Allen Thomas, 2 folders (Box 3)
    (royalty statements and contracts of Thomas's books published by Henry Holt and Co. and by D.C. Heath and Co.)
- Publications
  - Books, articles, reprints of the writings of Calvin Thomas, some containing marginal notations (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
December 17, 1914
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
April 20, 1917; May 2, 1917
Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.
November 5, 1908; February 17, 1911; April 22, 1911; January 17, 1912; January 16, 1912; December 10, 1912; November 30, 1914; January 30, 1915; April 5, 1917; May 4, 1917; May 7, 1917; September 25, 1917; October 10, 1917; November 24, 1917; November 27, 1917; December 30, 1918; November 4, 1919 (condolences); December 1, 1919 (condolences); December 8, 1919 (condolences)
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
June 11, 1910
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
September 8, 1925; July 27, 1927 (letters to Eleanor Thomas letters)
Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.
May 27, 1929; June 10, 1929; July 1, 1929; January 24, 1930; February 5, 1930 (letters to Eleanor Thomas letters)
Erskine, John Robert, 1869-1933.
December 16, 1912; November 5, 1919 (condolences)
Fisher, Dorothy Canfield, 1879-1958.
December 26 (1914?)
Gildersleeve, Virginia C.
1914 (response to President Butler's November 30 letter); November 5, 1919 (condolences)
Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928.
August 25, 1907
Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.
December 13, 1902
Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.
October 5, 1910; November 4, 1919 (condolences)
Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.
(letter to Eleanor Thomas) February 8, 1922
Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.
1914 (response to President Butler's November 30 letter); December 4, 1919 (condolences)
Thomas, Steven Van Renssler, 1831-1905.
October 9, 1898; April 16, 1899; November 7, 1901; May 17, 1903